# Basar Chowdhury

Master of Science, *Bioinformatics* <a href="https://github.com/sohailchd">https://github.com/sohailchd</a>

sohail.chd0202@gmail.com +1-857-930-1243 Boston, MA, 02130

### Summary

Backend Software engineer with 3 years of experience in design and development of backend systems and microservices. While working with Druva implemented backup features for cloud apps like google drive, Box and MS exchange. I have also created data pipelines and stream processing systems using spark and hadoop. Follows clean architecture and design principles while creating systems from scratch. Implemented machine learning project for pneumonia detection with convolutional neural networks. Performed statistical analysis of genomic data using R and NGS tools.

#### Skills

Languages: Python, Java, Golang

Frameworks: Flask, Requests, Java spring boot, ReactJS, golang web frameworks

Tools: Docker, Redis, Spark, Elasticsearch, AWS (EC2/S3/Dynamo), GIT, MySQL, MongoDB

Skills: Design and development of data processing systems, microservices and internal frameworks and

Services, AWS development, Agile and Scrum, Automated Testing, Linux system tools

Course work: Statistics, Genome sequencing, Advance Algorithms, Machine Learning, Distributed computing

## Work Experience

**Verys** (Software Engineer)

June 2019 to Dec 2019

- As a backend engineer created core system APIs for flight booking and integrated with cruise booking system
- Integrated Solr search with booking system
- Resolved and created some frontend features using ReactJS

**Druva** (Data backup and discovery / Software Engineer/ Unicorn startup)

29-Jan-2017 to 10-Aug-2018

- Developed APIs for endpoint backup and storage related services (AWS EC2)
- Developed cloudapps integration (Exchange mail/GDrive/Box) backup and restore APIs
- Developed microservices on AWS for parsing data before backup for compliance (HIPAA/PHI/Legal Hold)

Awards: Optimization of custom parser, reducing the data parsing tests from 4 hrs to 20 mins

**GSLabs** (Education and Stock Market CME / Software Engineer)

27-July-2013 to 27-July-2015

- Improved dashboard and analytics performance by integrating Redis
- Cloud migration of the legacy applications to spark for real time data processing
- Custom scheduler for running automated tests in multiple docker running in AWS

Awards: Created a custom scheduler for job execution for reporting and analysis on AWS

**Ubisoft** (Gaming and Entertainment / Test Engineer)

27-July-2013 to 27-July-2015

- Feature improvement/testing of payment gateway integration API for in game purchases
- Developed Internal network analysis tool for capturing multiplayer logs for PS4 development box
- Debugging and unit test cases for PS4 games ('The Crew' and 'Assassins creed black flag') in C++ and system tools in linux

#### Education

1. Master of Science, *Bioinformatics*, (Northeastern University, Boston)

May,2020

2. Bachelor Of Engineering, *Information Technology*, (University Of Pune, Pune)

May, 2013